{
  "de001" : {
    "front" : "List the classes of geographical classification in __Germany__. (4 points)",
    "back" : "* *Anbaugebiet* - designated regions for PDO wines\n* *Bereich* - a district within an *Anbaugebiet*\n* *Einzellage* - individual vineyard\n* *Grosslage* - group of vineyards",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de002" : {
    "front" : "How many *Anbaugebiet* are there in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "13",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de003" : {
    "front" : "What does *Qualitätswein bestimmter Anbaugebiete* (*QbA*) mean?",
    "back" : "*QbA* are wines produced from grapes grown exclusively in one of the 13 *Anbaugebiete*.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de004" : {
    "front" : "What does *Prädikatswein* mean in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "*Prädikatswein* indicates a quality wine with attributes defined according to the *Prädikat* levels it belongs to.\n\nGrapes must be from a single *Bereich*.\n\nMust enrichment is not allowed, however they may be sweetened post fermentation using *Süssreserve*.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de005" : {
    "front" : "What are the primary differences between *QbA* and *Prädikatswein*?",
    "back" : "h1 QbA\n\n* grapes from anywhere in the *Anbaugebiete*\n* must enrichment allowed\n\n\nh1 Prädikatswein\n\n* grapes must be from a single *Bereich*\n* must enrichment not allowed",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de006" : {
    "front" : "List the __German__ *Prädikat* levels.",
    "back" : "* *Kabinett*\n* *Spätlese*\n* *Auslese*\n* *Beerenauslese* (*BA*)\n* *Eiswein*\n* *Trockenbeereauslese* (*TBA*)",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "winestyle", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de007" : {
    "front" : "How much does *Prädikatswein* contribute to __Germany__ wine production?",
    "back" : "Varies between _30_ to _70_ percent of total, depending on vintage.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de008" : {
    "front" : "Describe a __German__ *Kabinett* *Riesling*.",
    "back" : "Light body, high acidity, balanced with residual sweetness.\nFlavours of green apple or citrus fruit.\n\nSweet styles have alcohol level between 8-9% abv, dry styles can reach 12% abv.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "pradikat", "law"]
  },
  "de009" : {
    "front" : "How does *Spätlese* differ from *Kabinett*?",
    "back" : "*Spätlese* (late-harvest) wines have more concentrated flavours.\nSweet styles will be sweeter than *Kabinett*.\nAlcohol level will have higher abv than *Kabinett* in either styles.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "pradikat", "law"]
  },
  "de010" : {
    "front" : "How does a *Spätlese* *Riesling* differ from a *Kabinett*?",
    "back" : "A *Spätlese* riesling have more concentrated flavours and body.\n\nFruit flavours will be riper - less green apple notes, more citrus aromas - and a hint of stone fruit (peach or apricot).",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de011" : {
    "front" : "What does the term *Goldkapsel* indicate?",
    "back" : "*Auslense* sweet wines that have an overt *botrytis* character.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de012" : {
    "front" : "What is the highest *Prädikat* level that a dry wine can be categorized into?",
    "back" : "*Auslese*",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de013" : {
    "front" : "True or False\n\n*BA* and *TBA* cannot be harvested mechanically.",
    "back" : "True.\n\nBy law, BA and TBA cannot be harvested mechanically.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de014" : {
    "front" : "At what temperature can grapes for *Eiswein* be harvested?",
    "back" : "-8°C",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de015" : {
    "front" : "How do the sweet wines of *Beerenauslese* and *Eiswein* differ?",
    "back" : "*BA* wines usually show body and complexity influenced by *botrytis*.\n\n*Eiswein* shows an intensely concentrated pure fruit flavours with very high levels of acidity.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "pradikat", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de016" : {
    "front" : "What vintage date is shown on an *Eiswein* label if the harvest takes place in January?",
    "back" : "The year in which the grapes are grown.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de017" : {
    "front" : "What grapes are selected for *TBA*?",
    "back" : "Individual grapes that have undergone extensive noble rot, where the fruit have shrivelled to tiny raisins.\n\nThis occurs only in the finest years.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "viniculture", "pradikat", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de018" : {
    "front" : "What do terms *Trocken* and *Halbtrocken* mean?",
    "back" : "*Trocken* - dry\n\n*Halbtrocken* - off-dry",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de018" : {
    "front" : "What does the term *Classic* indicate in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "*Classic* in __Germany__ indicate PDO wines of above average quality, with minimum alcohol level of 12%, and maximum residual sugar content of 15 g/L.\n\nGrapes must be a single variety, from a single vintage, and a single region.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de019" : {
    "front" : "What does the term *Selection* mean in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "*Selection* in __Germany__ mean dry PDO wines of a premium quality, at a maximum residual sugar level of 9 g/L.\n\nGrapes must have a must weight of _at least_ *Auslese* level and from a single *Einzellage*.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de020" : {
    "front" : "What is the minimum alcohol level required for a *Classic* designation in __Mosel__?",
    "back" : "11.5% in Mosel\n\n(12% everywhere else in __Germany__)",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "pradikat"]
  },
  "de021" : {
    "front" : "True or False\n\n*Verband Deutscher Prädikatsweingüter* (*VDP*) is part of national __German__ wine law.",
    "back" : "False\n\nVDP is an association of self-elected best producers throughout __Germany__.\n\nVDP terms are trademarks and is not part of __German__ wine law.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de022" : {
    "front" : "What does *Erste Lage* mean?",
    "back" : "*Erste Lage* indicate the best vineyards of the VDP members.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de018" : {
    "front" : "Which grape varieties are allowed for *Erste Lage* sites?",
    "back" : "Grape varieties for *Erste Lage* are limited to:\n\n* *Riesling*\n* *Silvaner*\n* *Grauburgunder*\n* *Weissburgunder*\n* *Spätburgunder*",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "varietals"]
  },
  "de019" : {
    "front" : "What are the __German__ names for *Pinot Gris*, *Pinot Blanc*, and *Pinot Noir*?",
    "back" : "| *Pinot Gris* | *Grauburgunder* |\n| *Pinot Blanc* | *Weissburgunder* |\n| *Pinot Noir* | *Spätburgunder*|",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "varietals", "pinot_gris", "pinot_blanc", "pinot_noir"]
  },
  "de020" : {
    "front" : "What does the term *GG* mean when it appears on a label?",
    "back" : "*GG* is an abbrevation for *Grosses Gewächs*.\n\nIt represents a dry wine from *Erstes Lage* sites.\n\nThe older term *Ertes Gewäche* is used in __Rheingau__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de021" : {
    "front" : "True or False\n\nVDP members can label sweet style *Prädikatswein* from their *Erste Lage* sites as *Grosses Gewäche*.",
    "back" : "False\n\nThe sweet wines can be labelled *Erste Lage*, but not *Grosses Gewäche*.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de022" : {
    "front" : "What climate factors contribute to __Germany__'s reputation for sweet wines?",
    "back" : "The long cool ripening period gives grapes time to develop high level of natural sugar while retaining their acidity.\n\nIn vintages with high humidity in the autumn, noble rot can develop.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "climate", "sweet_wine"]
  },
  "de023" : {
    "front" : "Why are the best sites in __Germany__ on steep slopes?",
    "back" : "__Germany__ have a *cool continental* climate with wet summers.\n\nThe best sites are on steep stony slopes to take advantage of natural drainage, and for maximum exposure to heat and sun.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture", "climate"]
  },
  "de024" : {
    "front" : "What is the most widely planted grape variety in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "*Riesling*",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "varietals", "riesling"]
  },
  "de025" : {
    "front" : "Why is *Riesling* ideal for late-harvest __German__ wines?",
    "back" : "*Riesling* ripens late (between October and November), is hardy, and has a naturally high level of acidity.\n\nThis is ideal for the long, cool ripening period in __Germany__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "varietals", "riesling", "climate"]
  },
  "de026" : {
    "front" : "What is a *Müller-Thurgau*?",
    "back" : "*Müller-Thurgau* is also known as *Rivaner*.\n\nIt is a cross made in the 1880s between *Riesling* and *Madeleine Royale*.\n\nIt produces an attractive, simple floral and fruity wine, but does not have the high level of acidity or intensity as a *Riesling*.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "varietals", "riesling", "rivaner"]
  },
  "de027" : {
    "front" : "Describe a *Silvaner* wine.",
    "back" : "*Silvaner* wines are moderate in acidity with neutral fruits and an earthy quality.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "varietals", "silvaner", "winestyle"]
  },
  "de028" : {
    "front" : "Which __German__ regions does *Spätburgunder* thrive in?",
    "back" : "Warmer areas in __Pfalz__ and __Baden__; and also (surprisngly) in __Ahr__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "varietals", "pinot_noir", "geography"]
  },
  "de029" : {
    "front" : "What factors contirbute to high bottle prices for quality __German__ wines?",
    "back" : "The finest vineyards are planted on the steep slopes of the river valleys, either terraced or planted directly up the slopes.\n\nAll vineyard work must be done by hand.\n\nQuality producers also restrict yields.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture"]
  },
  "de030" : {
    "front" : "What training methods do growers use on the slopes of __German__ valleys?",
    "back" : "On steeper slopes, vines are individually staked and canes tied in at the top -- to maximise grape exposure to light and air circulation.\n\nOn less severe slopes, vines are trained on wires.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture"]
  },
  "de031" : {
    "front" : "What methods do __German__ producers use to add richness and texture to their wines?",
    "back" : "Some producers use skin and lees contact to add body and richness to their wines.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viniculture"]
  },
  "de032" : {
    "front" : "True or False\n\n*Chaptalisation* is permitted for *Prädikatsweine*.",
    "back" : "False\n\n*Chaptalisation* is allowed for *Qualitätsweine*, but not for *Prädikatsweine*.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "law"]
  },
  "de033" : {
    "front" : "Which is *Süssreserve*?",
    "back" : "*Süssreserve* is unfermented grape juice must added to dry wine prior to bottling to increase sweetness and balance acidity.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viniculture"]
  },
  "de034" : {
    "front" : "Describe the geographic features that define the __Mosel__ region?",
    "back" : "The __Mosel__ region is roughly the valley of the __River Mosel__, from where it joins the __Rhine__ at __Koblenz__, to the __Luxemburg__ frontier; and its tributaries, the __Saar__ and the __Ruwer__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography", "mosel"]
  },
  "de035" : {
    "front" : "Describe a quality *Riesling* from the __Mosel__.",
    "back" : "Quality *Rieslings* from the __Mosel__ have a *light body*, *low alcohol*, *high acidity*, *medium sweetness*; and a flavour profile of *floral*, *green fruit* character.\n\n",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "mosel", "riesling"]
  },
  "de036" : {
    "front" : "What soil types are present in the __Nahe__?",
    "back" : "Soil in __Nahe__ is varied, and includes *slate*, *porphyry*, *quartz*, and coloured *sandstone* soils.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "expert",
    "tags" : ["de", "terroir"]
  },
  "de037" : {
    "front" : "How does a *Riesling* from __Nahe__ compare to its __Mosel__ cousin?",
    "back" : "__Nahe__ *Riesling* have the acidity of a __Mosel__, but with a slightly riper fruit character similar to the __Rhine__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "mosel", "riesling"]
  },
  "de038" : {
    "front" : "Describe a __Rheingau__ *Riesling*.",
    "back" : "__Rheingau__ *Riesling*: medium to full body and a ripe peach character.\n\n__Rheingau__ is also home to some of __Germany's__ best BA and TBA wines due to the humid conditions from the __Rhine__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "riesling"]
  },
  "de039" : {
    "front" : "Where are the majority of vineyards in the __Rheingau__?",
    "back" : "In a small stretch on the slopes of the __Rhine__, to the west of __Wiesbaden__ to the town of __Rüdesheim__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "expert",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography", "rheingau"]
  },
  "de040" : {
    "front" : "Why are wines of the __Rüdesheim__ considered the best of the __Rheingau__?",
    "back" : "Compared to the rest of the __Rheingau__, slopes at __Rüdesheim__ are much steeper and higher.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography", "viticulture"]
  },
  "de042" : {
    "front" : "Which villages produce the fullest bodied *Rieslings* in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "__Nierstein__ and __Oppenheim__ in __Rheinhessen__ produces the fullest-bodied *Rieslings* in __Germany__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "expert",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "riesling"]
  },
  "de043" : {
    "front" : "Name the three largest wine-growing regions in __Germany__.",
    "back" : "1. __Rheinhessen__\n2. Pfalz\n3. Baden",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture"]
  },
  "de044" : {
    "front" : "Why is the __Pfalz__ the driest region in __Germany__?",
    "back" : "__Pfalz__ is a narrow 80km strip running north from the French border and lies to the east of the __Haardt__ mountains, a continuation of the __Vosges__ moutains.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography"]
  },
  "de045" : {
    "front" : "What is the second most planted variety in __Pfalz__?",
    "back" : "*Dornfelder* (following *Riesling*)",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture"]
  },
  "de046" : {
    "front" : "Where are the most established vineyards of the __Pfalz__ situated?",
    "back" : "Surrounding villages of __Wachenheim__, __Forst__, __Deidesheim__, and __Ruppertsberg.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "expert",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography"]
  },
  "de047" : {
    "front" : "Why is __Baden__ known to produce the fullest bodied __German__ wines?",
    "back" : "__Baden__ is the warmest and most southerly wine region in __Germany__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography"]
  },
  "de048" : {
    "front" : "Which is the only __German__ region where red varieties are the majority?",
    "back" : "__Baden__",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "easy",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture"]
  },
  "de049" : {
    "front" : "Where are the best vineyards of __Baden__ situated?",
    "back" : "The best vineyards of __Baden__ are on the south-facing slope of the extinct volcano __Kaiserstuhl__, which is situated opposite __Colmar__ in __Alsace__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "expert",
    "tags" : ["de", "viniculture", "geography"]
  },
  "de050" : {
    "front" : "Why is __Silvaner__ the dominant quality variety in __Franken__?",
    "back" : "*Silvaner* is early flowering and ripening, compared to *Riesling* that struggles to ripen well in __Franken__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "normal",
    "tags" : ["de", "viticulture", "varietals", "silvaner", "riesling"]
  },
  "de051" : {
    "front" : "Where are the best sites of __Franken__?",
    "back" : "Best sites of __Franken__ are on south facing slopes across from __Würzburg__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "geography"]
  },
  "de052" : {
    "front" : "What wine style is the __Ahr__ known for?",
    "back" : "Elegant *Pinot Noirs*",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "pinot_noir"]
  },
  "de053" : {
    "front" : "What wine style is the __Mittelrhein__ known for?",
    "back" : "Light bodied dry *Rieslings*",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "riesling"]
  },
  "de052" : {
    "front" : "What wine style is the __Hessische Bergstrasse__ known for?",
    "back" : "*Rieslings* similar to the __Rheingau__.",
    "level" : "WSET3",
    "status" : "active",
    "difficulty" : "hard",
    "tags" : ["de", "winestyle", "riesling"]
  },
}
